Register of the Ernest W. Lefever Papers, 1933-2007
Hoover Institution Archives
Ernest W. Lefever papers
1933-2007
73090
Lefever, Ernest W., 1919-
173 manuscript boxes, 4 envelopes, 1 album box (71 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Writings, correspondence, interview summaries, notes, printed matter, and photographs, relating to pacifism in World War II, postwar African politics, United Nations intervention in the Congo, nuclear proliferation, American military and police-training aid to foreign countries, the role of religion in public policy, and activities of the Ethics and Public Policy Center.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1973.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United Nations--Congo (Democratic Republic); Nuclear weapons.; Military assistance, American.; Police training.; Africa.; Africa--Politics and government--1960-; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Armed Forces.; Congo (Democratic Republic); Congo (Democratic Republic)--Politics and government--1960-; Nuclear energy.; World War, 1939-1945--Conscientious objectors.; Conscientious objectors--United States.; Pacifism.; Religion and international affairs.; United States--Religion.; Ethics and Public Policy Center (Washington, D.C.); Peace.; World War, 1939-1945.
Biographical Note
1919 Nov. 12 Born, York, Pennsylvania
1945-1948 Field Secretary, World Alliance of Young Mens' Christian Associations, United Kingdom and West Germany
1952-1954 International affairs specialist, National Council of Churches
1956-1957 Faculty, Department of Government, University of Maryland
1957 Author, Ethics and U.S. Foreign Policy
1957-1959 Research staff, Acting Head, Foreign Affairs Division, Library of Congress
1959-1960 Foreign affairs staff, Senator Hubert H. Humphrey
1960 Author, Profile of American Politics
1960-1961 Research Associate, Washington Center for Foreign Policy Research, Johns Hopkins University
1961-1964 Senior Staff, Institute of Defense Analyses, Washington
1962 Editor, Arms and Arms Control
1964-1976 Senior Fellow, Foreign Policy Studies, Brookings Institute
1965 Author, Crisis in the Congo
1967 Author, Uncertain Mandate: Politics of the U.N. Congo Operation
1970 Author, Spear and Scepter: Army, Policy and Politics in Tropical Africa
1972 Author, Ethics and World Politics
1974 Author, TV and National Defense: An Analysis of CBS News
1976- Founder and President, Ethics and Public Policy Center, Washington, D.C.
1977 Author, Morality and Foreign Policy
1979 Author, Amsterdam to Nairobi: The World Council of Churches and the Third World
Author, Nuclear Arms in the Third World: U.S. Policy Dilemma
Editor, Will Capitalism Survive?
1980 Author, The CIA and the American Ethic
1981 Designate, Assistant Secretary of State for Human Rights and Humanitarian Affairs
1982 Author, The Apocalyptic Premise
1983 Author, Scholars, Dollars and Public Policy
Series Description
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1945-1986 (Box 38)
  Correspondence and some printed material relating to post-World War II relief and prisoners aid, and to the Hoover Institution. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1943-1990 (Box 1-13, 37, 42, 55)
  Drafts and printed copies of speeches and writings by Ernest W. Lefever. Includes related correspondence, notes, interviews, reports, reviews, printed and non-printed material, and other miscellany. Arranged chronologically.
- FOREIGN AFFAIRS STAFF, OFFICE OF SENATOR HUBERT H. HUMPHREY, 1959-1960 (Box 14-19)
  Correspondence, letters, memoranda, reports, speech transcripts, press releases, clippings, printed articles, notes, and miscellany. Includes letters, reports and speeches drafted by Ernest W. Lefever for Senator Humphrey. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1942-1983 (Box 20-30, 56-57)
  Speeches, memoranda, correspondence, letters, reports, printed articles, clippings, directories, interviews, newsletters, book lists, notes, and reviews relating to the activities of American pacifists during World War II, including YMCA involvement in the rehabilitation of German prisoners-of-war in Europe, 1946-1948, Africa, particularly the revolution in the Congo, 1960-1961, and United Nations efforts to restore order, nuclear proliferation, religion and ethics, the United States International Communications Agency, and United States military and public safety assistance to other countries. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- ETHICS AND PUBLIC POLICY CENTER, 1974-1989 (Box 31-41, 43-54)
  Drafts and printed copies of Ethics and Public Policy Center publications, drafts of unpublished works, a publication catalog, speeches, conference material, schedules, appointment books, reports, correspondence, minutes, notes, and printed material. Arranged by form.
- INCREMENTS (Box 58-173)
  Not yet described
- DECLASSIFIED RECORD, 1970 (Box 173)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1945-1986
  - General. Relates to post-World War II relief and prisoners aid, 1945-1948
    - General. Family letters (Box 38, Folder 1)
    - B-W (Folder 2-4)
  - Hoover Institution, 1978-1986 (Folder 5)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1943-1990
  - "Religion at the News Desk," Motive, 1951 Dec. Article and additional material, including letters, mimeographed broadcast transcripts (some co-authored by E. Lefever), schedules, printed articles and memoranda relating to a radio program sponsored by Yale University Divinity School, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - You, the Nation and the World. Letters and outline relating to a National Student YMCA-YWCA pamphlet (Folder 2)
  - "Protestants and United States Foreign Policy, 1925-1954: A Study of the Response of National Protestant Leaders to the Issues and Direction of U.S. Foreign Policy and of the Theoretical Assumptions which Underlay that Response," 1956. Draft and final typescript copies (Folder 3-4)
  - Intercollegian, 1956 Oct. Correspondence, news release, memoranda, background material on the 1956 election, and a typescript copy of an article written by Reinhold Niebuhr for this issue, which was edited by E. Lefever (Folder 5)
  - Ethics and U.S. Foreign Policy, 1957. Multiple drafts, correspondence, and miscellany, 1956-1958 (Box 2, Folder 1-7)
  - The World Crisis and American Responsiblity: Essays by Reinhold Niebuhr, edited by Ernest Lefever, 1958. Correspondence, outlines and miscellany, 1956-1959 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Arms and Arms Control, edited by Ernest Lefever, 1962. Correspondence, introduction, outlines and miscellany, 1961 (Folder 2-3)
  - "National Armaments and International Force," Institute for Defense Analysis, International Studies Division report (with others), 1963 July. Letters, interviews with U.S. military officials, notes, miscellaneous materials relating to trips, mimeographed report (4 vols.) (Folder 4-6)
  - "The Dilemma of Limited Options," 1963 Sept. Outlines and clippings, primarily relating to the Cuban missile crisis (Folder 7)
  - Crisis in the Congo, 1965. Promotional material and research records, 1963-1969 (Folder 8-10)
  - Speeches and writings relating to the Congo. Typescript and mimeographed copies, 1965-1971 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - United Nations Peacekeeping in the Congo, 1960-1964: An Analysis of Political, Executive and Military Control, U.S. Arms Control and Disarmament Agency report (with Wynfred Joshua), 1966
    - General
      - ACDA records, 1964-1966 (Folder 3)
      - Congo interviews, 1963-1965 (Folder 4)
      - Katanga problem. Interviews, notes, printed materials, letters, reports, 1962-1965 (Folder 5)
      - Trips
        - Afro-Asian trip, 1965 Jan.-March. Trip report (Folder 6)
        - Europe-North Africa trip, 1965 June-July. Correspondence and trip report (Folder 7-8)
    - Printed copy (Vols. 1-4) (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - "Role of Indigenous Military in Developing Countries," 1966-1970. Multiple drafts, correspondence, and an outline (Folder 4)
  - Uncertain Mandate: Politics of the U.N. Congo Operation, 1967. Letters, promotional material, reviews, and typescript (Folder 5-8)
  - "The Limits of U.N. Intervention in the Third World," Review of Politics, 1968. Reprint and outline (Folder 9)
  - "Orientation of A.I.D. Trainees at the Washington International Center," 1968 Oct. Mimeographed report (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "The Congo: Crisis of Decolonization--1960-1961," in William G. Andrews (ed.), International Crises: Four Case Studies, 1970. Correspondence and typescript, 1968-1970 (Folder 2)
  - Spear and Scepter: Army, Policy and Politics in Tropical Africa, 1970
    - General
      - General. Primarily lecture materials derived from the book; includes a book review, outlines, clippings, correspondence, a bibliography, and a condensed article published by the Brookings Institute (Folder 3)
      - Advisory Committee (Folder 4)
      - Basic records (Folder 5)
      - Book outline (Folder 6)
      - Correspondence with the Defense Department and William Gutteridge (Folder 6-7)
      - Interviews (Folder 8)
      - Photographs. Clippings. SEE ALSO: Photo card file (Folder 9)
      - Promotional materials (Folder 10)
      - Study proposal (Folder 11)
    - Drafts
      - Miscellaneous (Folder 12-13)
      - Final draft (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "Profile of the Critical Foreigner," 1969 April. Schedule, book review, clippings and a letter, 1967-1970 (Folder 2)
  - "Impact of Military Assistance on Developing Countries," 1971 Jan. Speech transcript (Folder 3)
  - "Defense and Development: Resource Competitors," 1972 March. Outline (Folder 4)
  - "Aspects of U.S. Military and Public Safety Assistance," 1972 Dec. Outline, notes, memorandum, report and printed article, 1972-1973 (Folder 5)
  - "U.S. Public Safety Assistance: An Assessment," U.S. Agency for International Development report, 1973
    - General
      - Lefever views, 1972 Nov. (Folder 6)
      - Public Safety field trip, 1972 Sept.-Oct. (Folder 7)
    - Report. Drafts (Folder 8)
    - Report. Drafts and final copy (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - "The CIA and American Foreign Policy," Lugano Review, 1975. Background materials and photocopy of the article (Folder 4)
  - "A Two-Edged Sword? U.S. Military Training and Advice in the Third World," 1976. Preliminary draft (Folder 5)
  - "A Two-Edged Sword? U.S. Military Training and Advice in the Third World," 1976. Drafts, comments and letters (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - "The Military Training Assistance Program," Annals of the American Academy, 1976 March. Printed copy, charts, and an outline (Folder 3)
  - Nuclear Arms in the Third World: U.S. Policy Dilemma, 1977. Outline and draft chapters 1 and 3 (Folder 4-8)
  - Nuclear Arms in the Third World: U.S. Policy Dilemma, 1977. Draft chapters 5-8, bibliography, appendices, final draft; also includes a later draft prepared for re-publication by the Ethics and Public Policy Center (?), 1977-1987 (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
  - Amsterdam to Nairobi: The World Council of Churches and the Third World, 1979. Drafts, proofs, a printed copy and correspondence (Box 11, Folder 1-6)
  - Will Capitalism Survive? edited by Ernest Lefever, 1979. Draft and printed copy (Folder 7-8)
  - The CIA and the American Ethic, 1980. Preliminary materials, draft chapters 1-2 (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
  - The CIA and the American Ethic, 1980. Draft chapters 3-5 and appendices, printed copy, and letters, 1975-1980 (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - "Space Defense is a Shield, Not a Sword," 1983. Drafts and clippings (Folder 7)
  - Scholars, Dollars and Public Policy: New Frontiers in Corporate Giving (with Raymond English and Robert L. Schuettinger), 1983. Printed article (Folder 8)
  - "Nairobi to Vancouver: The World Council of Churches and World Politics," 1987 June. Typescript (Box 37, Folder 5)
  - Increment, 1989 Dec. Correspondence, typescripts, printed material and miscellany, 1949-1987 (Folder 42)
  - Increment, 1990 Dec. Manuscript copy of Lefever's memoirs, and research papers relating to theology. Notes, outlines, typescripts, and printed material, 1943-1990 (Folder 55)
- FOREIGN AFFAIRS STAFF, OFFICE OF SENATOR HUBERT H. HUMPHREY, 1959-1960
  - General. Primarily work done by Ernest W. Lefever, with some biographical and administrative material relating to Hubert Humphrey
    - Biography (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and memoranda
      - Letters drafted by E.W. Lefever for Sen. Humphrey (Folder 2-3)
      - Letters between E.W. Lefever and Sen. Humphrey (Folder 4-5)
    - Schedules (Folder 6)
    - Speeches and writings. Background materials, drafts and letters relating to work done by E.W. Lefever for Sen. Humphrey
      - General
        - General (Folder 7-9)
        - Congressional Record (Box 15, Folder 1)
        - Extension of remarks by Humphrey (Folder 2)
        - Legislative Reference Service requests (Folder 3)
      - "Weapons of Free Men" (Folder 4)
      - "Works of Peace" (Folder 5)
  - Americans abroad (Folder 6)
  - Art and politics (Folder 7)
  - Civil rights (Folder 8)
  - Development Loan Fund (Folder 9)
  - Education for Peace (Folder 10)
  - Education in foreign policy (Folder 11)
  - Ethics and foreign policy (Folder 12)
  - Farm policy (Folder 13)
  - Food for Peace (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Foreign affairs (Folder 3)
  - Foreign economic policy (Folder 4)
  - Foreign information program (Folder 5)
  - Foreign policy (Folder 6)
  - Foreign Service Club (Folder 7)
  - Government operations (Folder 8)
  - Health for Peace (Folder 9)
  - Humphrey Committee (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Humphrey for President (Folder 2)
  - Humphrey Panel (Folder 3)
  - Immigration (Folder 4)
  - Intercultural relations (Folder 5)
  - International economic development (Folder 6)
  - International organization (Folder 7)
  - Labor (Folder 8)
  - Legislative program (Folder 9-10)
  - Moscow exhibition, 1959 (Folder 11)
  - Moscow festival (Folder 12)
  - Mutual security (Folder 13-14)
  - National defense (Folder 15)
  - National economy (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - National security (Folder 2)
  - North Atlantic Treaty Organization (Folder 3)
  - Political creed of Humphrey (Folder 4)
  - Political leadership (Folder 5)
  - Relations with the U.S.S.R. and military matters (Folder 6-7)
  - Science and technology (Folder 8)
  - United Nations (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Vienna Youth Festival, 1959 (Folder 2)
  - World Court (Folder 3)
  - World Refugee Year (Folder 4)
  - World trade (Folder 5)
  - World's Fair, 1964 (Folder 6)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1942-1983
  - Africa
    - African airlines and airports (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Congo, Republic of (Zaire)
      - Belgian assistance (Folder 2)
      - Belgian policies before independence (Folder 3)
      - Belgian position toward (Folder 4-5)
      - Dodd, Sen. Thomas J., statements and positions (Folder 6)
      - Education (Folder 7)
      - Elisabethville (Folder 8)
      - Katanga secession (Folder 9)
      - Miscellaneous clippings (Folder 10)
      - National Congolese Army (A.N.C.) (Folder 11)
      - O.N.U.C. telephone directory (Folder 12)
      - Police, 1960-1968 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      - United Nations atrocities (Folder 2)
      - United States military aid (Folder 3)
      - United States position toward (Folder 4)
      - Soviet policy (Folder 5)
    - Dahomey (Folder 6)
    - East African states (Folder 7)
    - Ethiopia
      - General (Folder 8-9)
      - Eritrean separatism (Folder 10)
      - Military, 1961-1969 (Folder 11)
      - Military and political aid to (Folder 12)
      - Miscellaneous clippings (Folder 13)
    - Ghana (Box 22, Folder 1-2)
    - Guinea (Folder 3)
    - Kenya (Folder 4)
    - Libya (Folder 5)
    - Senegal (Folder 6)
    - Sierra Leone (Folder 7)
    - Somalia (Folder 8)
    - Sudan (Folder 9)
    - Tanzania (Folder 10)
    - Uganda (Folder 11)
    - United Arab Republic (Folder 12)
    - Zambia (Folder 13)
  - Maryland. Reports, minutes, letters, pamphlet and miscellany relating to the Values Education Commission and the Social Studies Project, 1979-1983 (Box 23, Folder 1-2)
  - Nuclear Proliferation
    - General
      - General Primarily printed reports and articles, 1974-1977 (Folder 3-4)
      - Clippings
        - 1974-1975 (Folder 5)
        - 1975-1976 (Folder 6)
        - 1976-1977 (Box 24, Folder 1)
        - 1977-1978 (Folder 2)
    - Advisory Committee (Folder 3)
    - Defense Department (Folder 4)
    - Egypt (Folder 5)
    - Israel (Folder 6)
    - South Africa (Folder 7)
  - Religion
    - Christian Action International Affairs Committee (Box 25, Folder 1)
    - Christianity in Communist China (Folder 2)
    - Church Peace Union (Folder 3-4)
    - Church under fire, 1917-1938 (Folder 5)
    - Communists and civil liberties (Folder 6)
    - Conscientious objectors (Folder 7)
    - Conscientious objectors in prison (Folder 8)
    - Council on Religion in Higher Education (Folder 9)
    - Czechoslovakia (Folder 10-11)
    - Flank attack against Christianity, 1939-1950 (Box 26, Folder 1)
    - German opinion (Folder 2)
    - Hungary (Folder 3)
    - Labor and religion (Folder 4)
    - Labor and Religious Associates of the National Citizens Political Action Committee (Folder 5)
    - McCarthyism (Folder 6)
    - Protestant magazine (Folder 7)
    - Race situation, 1943-1950 (Folder 8)
    - Rand Corporation correspondence (Box 27, Folder 1)
    - Religion and Labor Foundation (Folder 2)
    - Religion in Germany (Folder 3)
    - Religious News Service (Folder 4)
    - Social Science Research Council (Folder 5)
    - Soviet Union - Religion (Folder 6)
    - U.S.S.R. policy in Germany (Folder 7)
    - United Student Christian Council (Folder 8)
    - Y.M.C.A. Social Education Committee (Folder 9)
  - United States International Communication Agency
    - General. Printed and non-printed reports, memoranda, notes, clippings, newsletters, book lists, charts, and letters, 1980-1983 (Folder 10-11)
    - General (Box 28, Folder 1-3)
    - Advisory Committee on Ethical Values. Letters, minutes and miscellany, 1982-1983 (Folder 4)
    - Advisory Committee on Policy Organizations. Letters, clippings, agenda and minutes, 1981-1982 (Folder 5)
    - Advisory Committee on Public Policy Foundations. Letters, memoranda, minutes and agenda, 1981-1983 (Folder 6)
  - United States - Military aid
    - General
      - Monographs (Folder 7)
      - Notes, 1968-1970 (Folder 8)
    - Advisory Committee (Folder 9)
    - Africa (Box 29, Folder 1)
    - Civic action (Folder 2)
    - Military pacts (Folder 3)
    - Military sales (Folder 4)
    - Political impact (Folder 5)
    - Title IX (Folder 6)
  - United States - Public safety assistance
    - Congressional interviews (Folder 7)
    - Country evaluation forms (Folder 8)
    - Criticism in the field (Folder 9)
    - Evaluation of assistance program, 1972 (Folder 10)
    - International Police Academy (Folder 11-12)
    - Latin American Assistant Secretaries of State (Folder 13)
  - Mitrione, Daniel
    - Kidnapping and murder (Folder 14)
    - Man and work (Folder 15)
    - Notes and manuscript (Folder 16)
    - Personal (Folder 17)
    - Personnel security regulations (Folder 18)
  - Police ethics (Folder 19)
  - Policemen's "working personality" (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Public safety aid study, 1971-1972 (Folder 2)
    - Public safety review (Folder 3)
    - Purpose and philosophy (Folder 4)
    - State of Siege (movie)
      - Background (Folder 5)
      - Follow-up meeting, 1973 April 24 (Folder 6)
      - Promotion (Folder 7)
      - Reviews (Folder 8)
    - Technical investigation course (Folder 9)
    - "The Thin Blue Line" (Folder 10)
    - Torture issues (Folder 11)
    - Tupamaros by Arturo C. Prozecanski (Folder 12)
    - Uruguay (Folder 13)
    - Varieties of civil violence (Folder 14)
  - World War II
    - German prisoners of war. Correspondence, reports, minutes, memoranda, clippings, pamphlets, and other printed matter relating to YMCA participation in rehabilitation efforts in Germany after the war, 1946-1948 (Folder 56)
    - Pacifism - United States. Correspondence, reports, and memoranda relating to the activities of American religious pacifist groups during the war, especially in work camps, 1939-1948. Includes material relating to the American Friends Service Commitee, the Church of the Brethern, and the Fellowship of Reconciliation (Folder 57)
- ETHICS AND PUBLIC POLICY CENTER, 1974-1987
  - General. Primarily administrative material. Letters, clipping, memoranda, notes, flyer and miscellany, 1982-1987 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Conference and meeting materials (Folder 2)
    - General. Schedules, flyers, notes, speech transcripts by Ronald Reagan and others, and miscellany, 1982-1987
    - Salute to Lech Walesa dinner, 1983 Oct. Correspondence with Edwin Meese, Caspar Weinberger, Max Kampelman, Lech Walesa and others, memoranda, schedules, lists, press releases, notes and miscellany, 1983-1986 (Box 37, Folder 1-2)
  - Conference and meeting materials (Contd.)
    - Tenth Anniversay dinner, 1986 Nov. Speeches, list, and clippings, 1986 (Folder 3)
  - Publications
    - General. Catalog and correspondence with prospective publishers, 1974-1987 (Box 31, Folder 3)
    - Non-printed material. Primarily unpublished manuscripts
      - Kraemer, Sven, "The Soviet Intelligence War," 1979 March. Typescript (Folder 4)
      - Bethell, Tom, "The New York Times," 1979 April (Folder 5)
      - Benestad, J. Brian, "The Pursuit of a Just Social Order: The Policy Statements of the United States Catholic Bishops, 1966-1980," 1979-1980. Two drafts and a memorandum (Folder 6)
      - Benestad, J. Brian, "The Pursuit of a Just Social Order" (Box 32, Folder 1)
      - Potter, Gary (ed.), "Pope John Paul II and Revolution," 1982. Typescript drafts, memoranda, printed and non-printed background material and reports (Folder 2-4)
      - Potter, Gary "Pope John Paul II and Revolution" (Box 33, Folder 1)
      - Hitchcock, James, "The Jesuits," 1980. Typescript, correspondence, reviews, clippings and miscellany (Folder 2-4)
      - Lefever, Ernest W. (ed.), "Reinvigorating Our Schools: A Challenge to Parents, Teachers and Policymakers," 1985 April. Excerpts from speeches by William J. Bennett, Ronald Reagan, and Ernest Lefever (Folder 5)
    - Printed material
      - General. News, Reviews and Comments on the Ethics and Public Policy Center. Clipping collection series (Folder 6-7)
      - Handleman, Howard, KGB Activities in the United States, n.d. Edited copy (Box 34, Folder 1)
      - Herz, Martin F., How the Cold War is Taught, 1978. Edited typescript and printed copy (Folder 2)
      - Kennan, George (ed.), Decline of the West?, 1978. Edited typescript, printed copy, and letter (Folder 3)
      - Novak, Michael, Values in an American Government Textbook, 1978. Edited typescript and printed copy (Box 35, Folder 1)
      - Berman, Ronald (ed.), Solzhenitsyn at Harvard, 1980. Edited typescript and printed copy (Folder 2)